Hello, and welcome!
In this video, we’ll be giving a brief introduction to regression.
So let’s get started.
Look at this dataset.
It&#39;s related to Co2 emissions from different cars.
It includes Engine size, number of Cylinders, Fuel Consumption and Co2 emission from various
automobile models.
The question is, &quot;Given this dataset, can we predict the Co2 emission of a car using
other fields, such as EngineSize or Cylinders?&quot;
Let’s assume we have some historical data from different cars, and assume that a car,
such as in row 9, has not been manufactured yet, but we&#39;re interested in estimating its
approximate Co2 emission, after production.
Is it possible?
We can use regression methods to predict a continuous value, such as CO2 Emission, using
some other variables.
Indeed, regression is the process of predicting a continuous value.
In regression there are two types of variables: a dependent variable and one or more independent
variables.
The dependent variable can be seen as the &quot;state&quot;, &quot;target&quot; or &quot;final goal&quot; we study
and try to predict, and the independent variables, also known as explanatory variables, can be
seen as the &quot;causes&quot; of those &quot;states&quot;.
The independent variables are shown conventionally by x; and the dependent variable is notated
by y.
A regression model relates y, or the dependent variable, to a function of x, i.e., the independent
variables.
The key point in the regression is that our dependent value should be continuous, and
cannot be a discreet value.
However, the independent variable or variables can be measured on either a categorical or
continuous measurement scale.
So, what we want to do here is to use the historical data of some cars, using one or
more of their features, and from that data, make a model.
We use regression to build such a regression/estimation model.
Then the model is used to predict the expected Co2 emission for a new or unknown car.
Basically there are 2 types of regression models: simple regression and multiple regression.
Simple regression is when one independent variable is used to estimate a dependent variable.
It can be either linear on non-linear.
For example, predicting Co2emission using the variable of EngineSize.
Linearity of regression is based on the nature of relationship between independent and dependent
variables.
When more than one independent variable is present, the process is called multiple linear
regression.
For example, predicting Co2emission using EngineSize and the number of Cylinders in
any given car.
Again, depending on the relation between dependent and independent variables, it can be either
linear or non-linear regression.
Let’s examine some sample applications of regression.
Essentially, we use regression when we want to estimate a continuous value.
For instance, one of the applications of regression analysis could be in the area of sales forecasting.
You can try to predict a salesperson&#39;s total yearly sales from independent variables such
as age, education, and years of experience.
It can also be used in the field of psychology, for example, to determine individual satisfaction
based on demographic and psychological factors.
We can use regression analysis to predict the price of a house in an area, based on its
size, number of bedrooms, and so on.
We can even use it to predict employment income for independent variables, such as hours of
work, education, occupation, sex, age, years of experience, and so on.
Indeed, you can find many examples of the usefulness of regression analysis in these
and many other fields or domains, such as finance, healthcare, retail, and more.
We have many regression algorithms.
Each of them has its own importance and a specific condition to which their application
is best suited.
And while we&#39;ve covered just a few of them in this course, it gives you enough base knowledge
for you to explore different regression techniques.
Thanks for watching!