Hello, and welcome! In this video, we’ll be covering multiple
linear regression.
As you know there are two types of linear regression models: simple regression and multiple
regression. Simple linear regression is when one independent
variable is used to estimate a dependent variable. For example, predicting Co2 emission using
the variable of EngineSize. In reality, there are multiple variables that
predict the Co2 emission. When multiple independent variables are present,
the process is called &quot;multiple linear regression.&quot; For example, predicting Co2 emission using
EngineSize and the number of Cylinders in the car’s engine.
Our focus in this video is on multiple linear regression.
The good thing is that multiple linear regression is the extension of the simple linear regression
model. So, I suggest you go through the Simple Linear Regression video first, if you haven’t
watched it already.
Before we dive into a sample dataset and see how multiple linear regression works, I want
to tell you what kind of problems it can solve; when we should use it; and, specifically,
what kind of questions we can answer using it.
Basically, there are two applications for multiple linear regression.
First, it can be used when we would like to identify the strength of the effect that the
independent variables have on a dependent variable.
For example, does revision time, test anxiety, lecture attendance, and gender, have any effect
on exam performance of students? Second, it can be used to predict the impact
of changes. That is, to understand how the dependent variable
changes when we change the independent variables. For example, if we were reviewing a person’s
health data, a multiple linear regression can tell you how much that person’s blood
pressure goes up (or down) for every unit increase (or decrease) in a patient’s body
mass index (BMI), holding other factors constant.
As is the case with simple linear regression, multiple linear regression is a method of
predicting a continuous variable. It uses multiple variables, called independent
variables, or predictors, that best predict the value of the target variable, which is
also called the dependent variable. In multiple linear regression, the target
value, y, is a linear combination of independent variables, x.
For example, you can predict how much Co2 a car might emit due to independent variables,
such as the car’s Engine Size, Number of Cylinders and Fuel Consumption.
Multiple linear regression is very useful because you can examine which variables are
significant predictors of the outcome variable. Also, you can find out how each feature impacts
the outcome variable. And again, as is the case in simple linear
regression, if you manage to build such a regression model, you can use it to predict
the emission amount of an unknown case, such as record number 9.
Generally, the model is of the form: y ̂=θ_0+ θ_1 x_1+ θ_2 x_2 and so on, up to ... +θ_n x_n.
Mathematically, we can show it as a vector form as well.
This means, it can be shown as a dot product of 2 vectors: the parameters vector and the
feature set vector.
Generally, we can show the equation for a multi-dimensional space as θ^T x, where θ
is an n-by-one vector of unknown parameters in a multi-dimensional space, and x is the
vector of the feature sets, as θ is a vector of coefficients, and is
supposed to be multiplied by x. Conventionally, it is shown as transpose θ.
θ is also called the parameters, or, weight vector of the regression equation … both
these terms can be used interchangeably. And x is the feature set, which represents
a car. For example x1 for engine size, or x2 for cylinders, and so on.
The first element of the feature set would be set to 1, because it turns the θ_0 into
the intercept or bias parameter when the vector is multiplied by the parameter vector.
Please notice that θ^T x in a one dimensional space, is the equation of a line.
It is what we use in simple linear regression. In higher dimensions, when we have more than
one input (or x), the line is called a plane or a hyper-plane.
And this is what we use for multiple linear regression.
So, the whole idea is to find the best fit hyper-plane for our data.
To this end, and as is the case in linear regression, we should estimate the values
for θ vector that best predict the value of the target field in each row.
To achieve this goal, we have to minimize the error of the prediction.
Now, the question is, &quot;How do we find the optimized parameters?&quot;
To find the optimized parameters for our model, we should first understand what the optimized
parameters are. Then we will find a way to optimize the parameters.
In short, optimized parameters are the ones which lead to a model with the fewest errors.
Let’s assume, for a moment, that we have already found the parameter vector of our
model. It means we already know the values of θ
vector. Now, we can use the model, and the feature
set of the first row of our dataset to predict the Co2 emission for the first car, correct?
If we plug the feature set values into the model equation, we find y ̂ .
Let’s say, for example, it returns 140 as the predicted value for this specific row.
What is the actual value? y=196. How different is the predicted value from
the actual value of 196? Well, we can calculate it quite simply, as
196-140, which of course = 56. This is the error of our model, only for one
row, or one car, in our case. As is the case in linear regression, we can
say the error here is the distance from the data point to the fitted regression model.
The mean of all residual errors shows how bad the model is representing the dataset.
It is called the mean squared error, or MSE.
Mathematically, MSE can be shown by an equation. While this is not the only way to expose the
error of a multiple linear regression model, it is one the most popular ways to do so.
The best model for our dataset is the one with minimum error for all prediction values.
So, the objective of multiple linear regression is to minimize the MSE equation.
To minimize it, we should find the best parameters θ, but how?
Okay, “How do we find the parameter or coefficients for multiple linear regression?”
There are many ways to estimate the value of these coefficients.
However, the most common methods are the ordinary least squares and optimization approach.
Ordinary least squares tries to estimate the values of the coefficients by minimizing
the “Mean Square Error.” This approach uses the data as a matrix and
uses linear algebra operations to estimate the optimal values for the theta.
The problem with this technique is the time complexity of calculating matrix operations,
as it can take a very long time to finish. When the number of rows in your dataset is
less 10,000 you can think of this technique as an option, however, for greater values,
you should try other faster approaches.
The second option is to use an optimization algorithm to find the best parameters.
That is, you can use a process of optimizing the values of the coefficients by iteratively
minimizing the error of the model on your training data.
For example, you can use Gradient Descent, which starts optimization with random values
for each coefficient. Then, calculates the errors, and tries to
minimize it through wise changing of the coefficients in multiple iterations.
Gradient descent is a proper approach if you have a large dataset.
Please understand, however, that there are other approaches to estimate the parameters
of the multiple linear regression that you can explore on your own.
After you find the best parameters for your model, you can go to the prediction phase.
After we found the parameters of the linear equation, making predictions is as simple
as solving the equation for a specific set of inputs.
Imagine we are predicting Co2 emission (or y) from other variables for the automobile
in record number 9. Our linear regression model representation
for this problem would be: y ̂=θ^T x. Once we find the parameters, we can plug them
into the equation of the linear model. For example, let’s use θ0 = 125, θ1 = 6.2,
θ2 = 14, and so on. If we map it to our dataset, we can rewrite
the linear model as &quot;Co2Emission=125 plus 6.2 multiplied by EngineSize plus 14 multiplied
by Cylinder,&quot; and so on. As you can see, multiple linear regression
estimates the relative importance of predictors. For example, it shows Cylinder has higher
impact on Co2 emission amounts in comparison with EngineSize.
Now, let’s plug in the 9th row of our dataset and calculate the Co2 emission for a car with
the EngineSize of 2.4. So Co2Emission=125 + 6.2 × 2.4 + 14 × 4
… and so on. We can predict the Co2 emission for this specific
car would be 214.1.
Now let me address some concerns that you might already be having regarding multiple
linear regression. As you saw, you can use multiple independent
variables to predict a target value in multiple linear regression.
It sometimes results in a better model compared to using a simple linear regression, which
uses only one independent variable to predict the dependent variable.
Now, the question is, &quot;How many independent variables should we use for the prediction?&quot;
Should we use all the fields in our dataset? Does adding independent variables to a multiple
linear regression model always increase the accuracy of the model?
Basically, adding too many independent variables without any theoretical justification may
result in an over-fit model. An over-fit model is a real problem because
it is too complicated for your data set and not general enough to be used for prediction.
So, it is recommended to avoid using many variables for prediction.
There are different ways to avoid overfitting a model in regression, however, that is outside
the scope of this video.
The next question is, “Should independent variables be continuous?”
Basically, categorical independent variables can be incorporated into a regression model
by converting them into numerical variables. For example, given a binary variable such
as car type, the code dummies “0” for “Manual” and 1 for “automatic” cars.
As a last point, remember that “multiple linear regression” is a specific type of
linear regression. So, there needs to be a linear relationship
between the dependent variable and each of your independent variables.
There are a number of ways to check for linear relationship.
For example, you can use scatterplots, and then visually check for linearity.
If the relationship displayed in your scatterplot is not linear, then, you need to use non-linear
regression.
This concludes our video. Thanks for watching.