Hello, and welcome!
In this video, we’ll be covering the process of building decision trees.
So let’s get started!
Consider the drug dataset again.
The question is, “How do we build the decision tree based on that dataset?”
Decision trees are built using recursive partitioning to classify the data.
Let’s say we have 14 patients in our dataset.
The algorithm chooses the most predictive feature to split the data on.
What is important in making a decision tree, is to determine “which attribute is the
best, or more predictive, to split data based on the feature.”
Let’s say we pick “Cholesterol” as the first attribute to split data.
It will split our data into 2 branches.
As you can see, if the patient has high “Cholesterol,” we cannot say with high confidence that Drug B
might be suitable for him.
Also, if the Patient’s “Cholesterol” is normal, we still don’t have sufficient
evidence or information to determine if either Drug A or Drug B is, in fact, suitable.
It is a sample of bad attribute selection for splitting data.
So, let’s try another attribute.
Again, we have our 14 cases.
This time, we pick the “sex” attribute of patients.
It will split our data into 2 branches, Male and Female.
As you can see, if the patient is Female, we can say Drug B might be suitable for her
with high certainty.
But, if the patient is Male, we don’t have sufficient evidence or information to determine
if Drug A or Drug B is suitable.
However, it is still a better choice in comparison with the “Cholesterol” attribute, because
the result in the nodes are more pure.
It means, nodes that are either mostly Drug A or Drug B.
So, we can say the “Sex” attribute is more significant than “Cholesterol,” or
in other words, it’s more predictive than the other attributes.
Indeed, “predictiveness” is based on decrease in “impurity” of nodes.
We’re looking for the best feature to decrease the ”impurity” of patients in the leaves,
after splitting them up based on that feature.
So, the “Sex” feature is a good candidate in the following case, because it almost found
the pure patients.
Let’s go one step further.
For the Male patient branch, we again test other attributes to split the subtree.
We test “Cholesterol” again here.
As you can see, it results in even more pure leaves.
So, we can easily make a decision here.
For example, if a patient is “Male”, and his “Cholesterol” is “High”, we can
certainly prescribe Drug A, but if it is “Normal”, we can prescribe Drug B with high confidence.
As you might notice, the choice of attribute to split data is very important, and it is
all about “purity” of the leaves after the split.
A node in the tree is considered “pure” if, in 100% of the cases, the nodes fall into
a specific category of the target field.
In fact, the method uses recursive partitioning to split the training records into segments
by minimizing the “impurity” at each step.
”Impurity” of nodes is calculated by “Entropy” of data in the node.
So, what is “Entropy”?
Entropy is the amount of information disorder, or the amount of randomness in the data.
The entropy in the node depends on how much random data is in that node and is calculated
for each node.
In decision trees, we&#39;re looking for trees that have the smallest entropy in their nodes.
The entropy is used to calculate the homogeneity of the samples in that node.
If the samples are completely homogeneous the entropy is zero and if the samples are
equally divided, it has an entropy of one.
This means, if all the data in a node are either Drug A or Drug B, then the entropy
is zero, but if half of the data are Drug A and other half are B, then the entropy is
one.
You can easily calculate the entropy of a node using the frequency table of the attribute
through the Entropy formula, where P is for the proportion or ratio of a category, such
as Drug A or B. Please remember, though, that you don’t
have to calculate these, as it’s easily calculated by the libraries or packages that
you use.
As an example, let’s calculate the entropy of the dataset before splitting it.
We have 9 occurrences of Drug B and 5 of Drug A.
You can embed these numbers into the Entropy formula to calculate the impurity of the target
attribute before splitting it.
In this case, it is 0.94.
So, what is entropy after splitting?
Now we can test different attributes to find the one with the most “predictiveness,”
which results in two more pure branches.
Let’s first select the “Cholesterol” of the patient and see how the data gets split,
based on its values.
For example, when it is “normal,” we have 6 for Drug B, and 2 for Drug A.
We can calculate the Entropy of this node based on the distribution of drug A and B,
which is 0.8 in this case.
But, when Cholesterol is “High,” the data is split into 3 for drug B and 3 for drug A.
Calculating its entropy, we can see it would be 1.0.
We should go through all the attributes and
calculate the “Entropy” after the split, and then chose the best attribute.
Ok, let’s try another field.
Let’s choose the Sex attribute for the next check.
As you can see, when we use the Sex attribute to split the data, when its value is “Female,”
we have 3 patients that responded to Drug B, and 4 patients that responded to Drug A.
The entropy for this node is 0.98 which is not very promising.
However, on other side of the branch, when the value of the Sex attribute is Male, the
result is more pure with 6 for Drug B and only 1 for Drug A.
The entropy for this group is 0.59.
Now, the question is, between the Cholesterol and Sex attributes, which one is a better
choice?
Which one is better as the first attribute to divide the dataset into 2 branches?
Or, in other words, which attribute results in more pure nodes for our drugs?
Or, in which tree, do we have less entropy after splitting rather than before splitting?
The “Sex” attribute with entropy of 0.98 and 0.59, or the “Cholesterol” attribute
with entropy of 0.81 and 1.0 in its branches?
The answer is, “The tree with the higher information gain after splitting.&quot;
So, what is information gain?
Information gain is the information that can increase the level of certainty after splitting.
It is the entropy of a tree before the split minus the weighted entropy after the split
by an attribute.
We can think of information gain and entropy as opposites.
As entropy, or the amount of randomness, decreases, the information gain, or amount of certainty,
increases, and vice-versa.
So, constructing a decision tree is all about finding attributes that return the highest
information gain.
Let’s see how “information gain” is calculated for the Sex attribute.
As mentioned, the information gain is the entropy of the tree before the split, minus
the weighted entropy after the split.
The entropy of the tree before the split is 0.94.
The portion of Female patients is 7 out of 14, and its entropy is 0.985.
Also, the portion of men is 7 out of 14, and the entropy of the Male node is 0.592.
The result of a square bracket here is the weighted entropy after the split.
So, the information gain of the tree if we use the “Sex” attribute to split the dataset
is 0.151.
As you can see, we will consider the entropy over the distribution of samples falling under
each leaf node, and we’ll take a weighted average of that entropy – weighted by the
proportion of samples falling under that leaf.
We can calculate the information gain of the tree if we use “Cholesterol” as well.
It is 0.48.
Now, the question is, “Which attribute is more suitable?”
Well, as mentioned, the tree with the higher information gain after splitting.
This means the “Sex” attribute.
So, we select the “Sex” attribute as the first splitter.
Now, what is the next attribute after branching by the “Sex” attribute?
Well, as you can guess, we should repeat the process for each branch, and test each of
the other attributes to continue to reach the most pure leaves.
This is the way that you build a decision tree!
Thanks for watching!