Hello, and welcome!
In this video we will learn a machine learning method called Support Vector Machine (or SVM),
which is used for classification.
So let’s get started.
Imagine that you’ve obtained a dataset containing characteristics of thousands of human cell
samples extracted from patients who were believed to be at risk of developing cancer.
Analysis of the original data showed that many of the characteristics differed significantly
between benign and malignant samples.
You can use the values of these cell characteristics in samples from other patients to give an
early indication of whether a new sample might be benign or malignant.
You can use support vector machine, or SVM, as a classifier, to train your model to understand
patterns within the data, that might show benign or malignant cells.
Once the model has been trained, it can be used to predict your new or unknown cell with
rather high accuracy.
Now, let me give you a formal definition of SVM.
A Support Vector Machine is a supervised algorithm that can classify cases by finding a separator.
SVM works by first, mapping data to a high-dimensional feature space so that data points can be categorized,
even when the data are not otherwise linearly separable.
Then, a separator is estimated for the data.
The data should be transformed in such a way that a separator could be drawn as a hyperplane.
For example, consider the following figure, which shows the distribution of a small set
of cells, only based on their Unit Size and Clump thickness.
As you can see, the data points fall into two different categories.
It represents a linearly, non-separable, dataset.
The two categories can be separated with a curve, but not a line.
That is, it represents a linearly, non-separable dataset, which is the case for most real-world
datasets.
We can transfer this data to a higher dimensional space … for example, mapping it to a 3-dimensional
space.
After the transformation, the boundary between the two categories can be defined by a hyperplane.
As we are now in 3-dimensional space, the separator is shown as a plane.
This plane can be used to classify new or unknown cases.
Therefore, the SVM algorithm outputs an optimal hyperplane that categorizes new examples.
Now, there are two challenging questions to consider:
1) How do we transfer data in such a way that a separator could be drawn as a hyperplane?
and 2) How can we find the best/optimized hyperplane
separator after transformation?
Let’s first look at “transforming data” to see how it works.
For the sake of simplicity, imagine that our dataset is 1-dimensional data, this means,
we have only one feature x.
As you can see, it is not linearly separable.
So, what we can do here?
Well, we can transfer it into a 2-dimensional space.
For example, your can increase the dimension of data by mapping x into a new space using
a function, with outputs x and x-squared.
Now, the data is linearly separable, right?
Notice that, as we are in a two dimensional space, the hyperplane is a line dividing a
plane into two parts where each class lays on either side.
Now we can use this line to classify new cases.
Basically, mapping data into a higher dimensional space is called kernelling.
The mathematical function used for the transformation is known as the kernel function, and can be
of different types, such as: Linear, Polynomial, Radial basis function (or RBF), and Sigmoid.
Each of these functions has its own characteristics, its pros and cons, and its equation, but the
good news is that you don’t need to know them, as most of them are already
implemented in libraries of data science programming languages.
Also, as there&#39;s no easy way of knowing which function performs best with any given dataset,
we usually choose different functions in turn and compare the results.
Now, we get to another question, specifically, “How do we find the right or optimized separator
after transformation?”
Basically, SVMs are based on the idea of finding a hyperplane that best divides a dataset into
two classes, as shown here.
As we’re in a 2-dimensional space, you can think of the hyperplane as a line that linearly
separates the blue points from the red points.
One reasonable choice as the best hyperplane is the one that represents the largest separation,
or margin, between the two classes.
So, the goal is to choose a hyperplane with as big a margin as possible.
Examples closest to the hyperplane are support vectors.
It is intuitive that only support vectors matter for achieving our goal; and thus, other
training examples can be ignored.
We try to find the hyperplane in such a way that it has the maximum distance to support
vectors.
Please note, that the hyperplane and boundary decision lines have their own equations.
So, finding the optimized hyperplane can be formalized using an equation which involves
quite a bit more math, so I’m not going to go through it here, in detail.
That said, the hyperplane is learned from training data using an optimization procedure
that maximizes the margin; and like many other problems, this optimization problem can also
be solved by gradient descent, which is out of scope of this video.
Therefore, the output of the algorithm is the values ‘w’ and ‘b’ for the line.
You can make classifications using this estimated line.
It is enough to plug in input values into the line equation, then, you can calculate
whether an unknown point is above or below the line.
If the equation returns a value greater than 0, then the point belongs to the first class,
which is above the line, and vice versa.
The two main advantages of support vector machines are that they’re accurate in high
dimensional spaces; and, they use a subset of training points in the decision function
(called support vectors), so it’s also memory efficient.
The disadvantages of support vector machines include the fact that the algorithm is prone
for over-fitting, if the number of features is much greater than the number of samples.
Also, SVMs do not directly provide probability estimates, which are desirable in most classification
problems.
And finally, SVMs are not very efficient computationally, if your dataset is very big, such as when
you have more than one thousand rows.
And now, our final question is, “In which situation should I use SVM?”
Well, SVM is good for image analysis tasks, such as image classification and handwritten
digit recognition.
Also SVM is very effective in text-mining tasks, particularly due to its effectiveness
in dealing with high-dimensional data.
For example, it is used for detecting spam, text category assignment, and sentiment analysis.
Another application of SVM is in Gene Expression data classification, again, because of its
power in high dimensional data classification.
SVM can also be used for other types of machine learning problems, such as regression,
outlier detection, and clustering.
I’ll leave it to you to explore more about these particular problems.
This concludes this video … Thanks for watching!